iPhoneComposer Performance 

Jules Testard and Hsin-Ming Lin
UCSD CPMC #203 and #365
December 17, 2014

The iPhoneComposer is a mobile-based machine musical improvisation application designed for real-time performance. The iPhoneComposer should be seen as an instrument in which the performer instructs the machine on how to generate musical notes, rather than by specifying the notes themselves. These instructions are given in the form of pitch, rhythm, chord and velocity patterns. If described in one sentence, the iPhoneComposer is an attempt to have a score based on a performance rather than a performance based on a score.

In this experimental piece, we try to demonstrate most functions which are currently implemented while presenting some musical elements and distinct structures through two performers’ improvisation. We designed six presets and borrowed several pitches from “Dies Irea” plainchant as one of themes. The tonal center is G minor, but performers can make free transition and modulation individually or together at several sections. It starts from repetitions and basic transformations e.g. octave change, inverse, random and cyclic. Next, more repeated patterns come with transformations of pitch, rhythm, or amplitude. It reaches climax by improvised amplitude changes with polyphonic pitches. The ending fades out by amplitude and occurrence diminishing.

Please visit our repository (https://github.com/jtestard/iPhoneComposer) for more information about the algorithms, graphic user interfaces, source codes, etc.
